Irendra Radjawali

radjawali@protonmail.com | +62 813 8171 4337

Political-Ecology | Network & Data Science | Complexity Science | Techno & Digital Politics | Artificial Intelligence & Machine Learning | Social-Ecological System Analysis | Human-Geography | Governance | Mis/Disinformation Study

Short Profile

Teaching Political-Ecology & GeoPolitics,

Teaching Big Data Analysis & Network – I speak Data & Network Tinkerer, Do-It-Yourself [DIY] & Do-It-With-Others [DIWO] enthusiast.

Techno-politic & Data-politic Research

Fascinated by complexity science,

Online social media analyst,

Written and Verbal communicator,

Collective Achiever, Team Player, Clear Goal and Target
Drone & Data Academy for Humanity – Co-founder

Artificial Intelligence & Machine Learning for humanity enthusiast Pragmatic – Idealistic Nexus

Professional Skills

- Political-Ecology & Action Research
- Social Network Analysis [Gephi, R, Pajek, Netlogo, NodeXL, Python]
- Online Social Media Analysis
- Digital Propaganda, Virality Research
- Data Mining / Web Scraping [Python, R, Gephi]
- Social Simulation / Agent-Based Model [NetLogo,R]
- Quantitative Data Analysis [R & Python]
- Cartography / Counter Mapping with Drones
- Geographic Information System / GIS [ArcGIS, QGIS, R]
- Data Visualization [Carto, Tableau, R, Python]

Employment History

Research Coordinator – Localizing Human Rights and Gender Equality in SDG Context. Raoul Wallenberg Institute [2020] Researcher for Directorate General of Law Enforcement KLHK on Modelling (system dynamics) of forest harvesting tools regulations [2020]

Principal Researcher for KEMITRAAN and CLUA on Drivers of Deforestation in Indonesia [2020]

Data Scientist Consultant for SOLIDAR & CARITAS on Disaster Risk Reduction assessment in Central Sulawesi [2020]

Coordinating Researcher for Raoul Wallenberg Institute on Localizing Human Rights and Gender Equality in SDG Context in 3 countries [2020]

Researcher for Ministry of Forestry Indonesia under MFP4 Program on Assessment of Deforestation Tools [2020]

Researcher for Ministry of Forestry Indonesia on Forest Fire Prevention System [2020]

Reviewer for Publish What You Pay Indonesia on GIS Manual for community and grass root activists [2020

KEMITRAAN – PARTNERSHIP for GOVERNANCE REFORM

Data Scientist Consultant in Peatland Restoration Program [2016-2019]

With Peatland Restoration Agency: Geospatial & Data Analyst consultant for the establishment of Peatland Caring Village [Desa Peduli Gambut] Project [2016-2019]

Life Philosophy

The Ultimate Sophistication is Simplicity **Leonardo Da Vinci**

Education & Academic

- Ph.D [cand.] in Complexity Science, ISCTE [University Institute] Lisbon —Portugal
- Researcher in Political-Ecology [2011-2015], Bonn University – Germany
- Ph.D researcher in Political-Ecology [2007-2011],
 University of Bremen & Center for Tropical Marine Ecology,
 Bremen, Germany
- Summer School in Agent-Based Model [2009], Technische Universiteit Dresden – Germany
- Post-Graduate Courses in Global Environmental Governance [2009], SENSE [Research School for Socio-Economic and Natural Sciences of The Environment] – The Netherlands
- Master courses in Geography [2005-2006], Universite
 Paris I Pantheon-Sorbonne France
- Master in Urban & Regional Planning [2002-2004],
 Bandung Institute of Technology Indonesia
- Bachelor in Civil Engineering [1993-2001], Bandung Institute of Technology – Indonesia

Passions



Artificial Intelligence & Machine Learning



Network & Data Science



Big Data Analytic



1

F

Sports [running, martial arts, basketball, ultimate frisbee, slacklining]

Teaching

Music [Listening & Playing]



Nature

Engineering [Drones]



Geography

Employment History

Researcher / Writer in developing alternative to Business as Usual Economic Development in Indonesia – "Seeing The Unseen: Inequality and Economic Development in Indonesia" [2017-2018]

Geospatial Analyst Consultant – for [counter]mapping with drones in Peatland Restoration Program Villages [2017-2019] Researcher Consultant in developing Adaptation to Climate Change proposal studies in Indonesia [2017-2018] Researcher Consultant in Promoting Digital Sanity – Combating Information Manipulation and Online Extremism in Indonesia [2017-2019]

Post Disaster [Earthquake] humanitarian action & rapid assessment with drones in Lombok [2018]

KEMITRAAN With MINISTRY of ENVIRONMENT & FORESTRY, REPUBLIC of INDONESIA

Data Scientist and Digital Expert in acceleration & Implementation of Social Forestry Program [2018-2019]

Drone mapping & Geospatial expert for Social Forestry and Agrarian Reform in Banjarmasin [2018]

Drone mapping & Data Scientist for Law Enforcement in Tesso Nilo National Park [2017]

Drone mapping and Data Scientist for post natural disaster assessment in Bima, Nusa Tenggara Timur [2017]

CONSULTANT – Drone mapping for post-mining assessment in Karawang, West Java [2016]

Consultant for MoEF Drone Skuad Establishment for Directorate General of Law Enforcement & Directorate General of Social Forestry and Environmental Partnership

MINISTRY OF PUBLIC WORKS, REPUBLIC of INDONESIA

CONSULTANT – Drone mapping for post eruption rapid assessment of Sinabung volcano in North Sumatera [2016]

SWANDIRI INSTITUTE [In PONTIANAK]

With Publish What You Pay Indonesia - Researcher in cocreating transparency and accountability of revenue and spending in extractive resources sectors [2014].

With Samdhana Institute – Researcher in promoting spatial transparency for customary and indigenous land protection and acknowledgement in West Kalimantan Province, Indonesia [2014]

With The Asia Foundation – Researcher in examining actors and centrality: Social network analysis of land and forest management in West Kalimantan Province, Indonesia [2014]

Research on towards spatial transparency in extractive industries in West Kalimantan Province, Indonesia in the context of Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative [EITI].

INSTITUTE for ORIENTAL & ASIAN STUDIES, BONN UNIVERSITY, GERMANY

Research on the political ecology of Kapuas River, West Kalimantan Province, Indonesia [2011-2015].

DAI - INDONESIA

Project on Capitalizing Knowledge Connecting Communities. A Stocktaking of sustainable community-based forest management in Kalimantan, Indonesia [2009].

LEIBNIZ CENTER for TROPICAL MARINE ECOLOGY, BREMEN, GERMANY

Science for the protection of Indonesian marine and coastal ecosystem [SPICE] project [2007-2011].

Publication

- 1. Radjawali, I., and Pye, O. (2017). Drone for Justice: Inclusive Technology and River-Related Action Research along The Kapuas. Geographica Helvetica
- 2. Radjawali, I., Pye, O., and Flitner, M. (2017). Recognition through Reconnaissance? Using drones for counter-mapping in Indonesia. Journal of Peasant Studies.
- 3. Radjawali, I., and Hoeing, A. (2015). Umweltaktivismus in Indonesien. In Stange, G., Jordan, R., and Grossmann, K. (Eds.). Handbuch Indonesien. Horlemann Verlag.
- 4. Hoeing, A. & Radjawali, I. (2017). Livelihood Strategies: Access and Power among Forest-Dependent Dayak Communities. Incoming Book "Change and Continuity in Dayak Society".
- 5. Glaser, M., Breckwoldt, A., Deswandi, R., **Radjawali, I.**, Baitoningsih, W. & Ferse, S.C.A. (2015). Of Exploited Reefs and Fisher A Holistic View on Participatory Coastal and Marine Management in an Indonesian Archipelago. Ocean & Coastal Management 116.
- 6. Radjawali, I., Pye, O. (2015). Counter mapping land grabs with community drones in Indonesia. Conference Paper. Land Grabbing: Perspectives from East and Southeast Asia.
- 7. Pye, O., Radjawali, I., Julia (2015). Land grabs and the river. Conference Paper. Land Grabbing: Perspectives from East and Southeast Asia.
- 8. Radjawali, I., Hermawansyah & Munandar, A. (2014) The Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative: Towards Spatial Transparency. Rapid Socio-spatial assessment of extractive industries in West Kalimantan, Indonesia. Final Report. Published by Swandiri Institute and PWYP [Publish What You Pay] Indonesia.
- 9. Radjawali, I., Hermawansyah & Munandar, A. (2014) The Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative: Towards Spatial Transparency. Rapid Socio-spatial assessment of extractive industries in West Kalimantan, Indonesia. Policy Brief. Published by Swandiri Institute and PWYP [Publish What You Pay] Indonesia.
- 10. Hendrawan, H., Radjawali, I. & Hermawansyah (2014) Actor and centrality: Social network analysis of land and forest management in West Kalimantan, Indonesia. Final Report. Published by Swandiri Institute, The Asia Foundation and Epistema Institute.
- 11. Lukas, M., Julia, **Radjawali, I**., Pye, O., Flitner, M. (2013) The Conflict laden multi-functionality of the Kapuas River in Kalimantan, Indonesia. Austrian Journal of Southeast Asian Studies.
- 12. Plitschka, T., Radjawali, I. (2013) Progress and challenges of combating climate change in Indonesia an Interview with Prof. Rachmat Witoelar. Austrian Journal of Southeast Asian Studies.
- 13. Radjawali, I. (2012) Examining local conservation and development: Live reef food fishing in Spermonde Archipelago, Indonesia. Journal of Integrated Coastal Zone Management Vol. 12, Issue 4.
- 14. Radjawali, I. (2011) Social networks and live reef food fish (LRFF) trade: examining sustainability. Journal of Indonesian Social Sciences and Humanities.
- 15. Glaser, M., Radjawali, I., Ferse, S., Glaeser, B. (2010) Nested participation in hierarchical societies? Lessons for social-ecological research and management. International Journal of Society Systems Science, Vol. 2, No.4.
- 16. Radjawali, I. (2010) Reconsidering development, coping with uncertainties: reef fishery in Spermonde, South Sulawesi (Indonesia). Reconsidering Development, interdisciplinary e-journal based at the University of Minnesota.
- 17. The Danish Board of Technology (2009) Policy Report: World Wide Views on Global Warming From the World's Citizens to the Climate Policy-Makers. www.wwviews.org
- 18. Ferse, S., Radjawali I., Schwerdtner-Manez Costa, K., Neil, M., Glaser, M., Socio-Economic Drivers in the Coral Reef Fishery of Spermonde, South Sulawesi, Indonesia. Abstract submitted to Oceans Past II Conference, Vancouver, May 2009.

TALKS [selected]

2020

- Digital Detox and Digital Security, Jakarta
- The Age Of Surveillance Capitalism, Online

2019

- International Forum for The Advancement of Culture [IFAC], Jakarta.
- Kemah Budaya Kaum Muda [Youth Cultural Camp], Yogyakarta
- Social Forestry Festival [Jakarta & South Sulawesi]
- Universal Basic Income Conference, [Indonesia, India, USA]
- Big Data & Industrial Revolution 4.0, Jakarta.
- Indonesia Development Forum, Jakarta.

2018

- Political Ecology, Social-Ecological Crisis & Planning, London.
- Counter Mapping With Drones, Kyoto

2017

- Open Southeast Asia, Bonn
- Open Imagery Network, Seattle
- Big Data, Online Social Media & Intolerance, Jakarta
- Precision Conservation with Drones [WWF], Jakarta
- Inclusive Technology & Precision Urbanism, Jakarta

Language Proficiency

Listening Speaking Reading Writing

Indonesian	Excellent	Excellent	Excellent	Excellent
English	Excellent	Excellent	Excellent	Excellent
French	Fluent	Fluent	Fluent	Fluent
German	Good	Good	Basic	Basic
Javanese	Fluent	Fluent	Fluent	Fluent
Sundanese	Fluent	Fluent	Fluent	Fluent
Spanish	Basic	Basic	Basic	Basic

Ongoing Research

- The Emergence of Online and Offline Mis/Dis Information [Ph.D research at ISCTE, Lisbon]
- Network Analysis of Online Mis/Dis-information in Indonesia
- Understanding the dynamics of Religious Online Mis/Dis-Information in Indonesia
- Agent-Based Model of Online Mis/Dis-Information in Indonesia – The COVID19 case [complexity science]
- Chapter on Digital Sanity and Countering Online Mis/Dis Information. To be published in PRISMA.
- Data and Techno Politics in Indonesia

Public Outreach

Precision Agriculture with Drones

- http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2015/09/17/ dronesapplied-agriculturalpurposes.html
- http://www.mongabay.co.id/2015/09/26/dronepertanianteknologi-deteksi-dini-untukberbagai persoalan-tanaman/
- http://www.antaranews.com/berita/518401/dronemulaidigunakan-untuk-deteksikesehatan-tanaman

Counter Mapping with Drones

- Drones and Aerial Observation: New Technology for Property Rights, Human Rights, and Global Development A Primer. New America. July 2015. http://drones.newamerica.org/primer/
- Dayaks and Drones: Documentary Movie on advocacy and spatial transparency with the indigenous communities in Borneo.
- http://www.mongabay.co.id/2015/10/28/droneteknologiinklusif-untuk-masyarakat/
- http://www.mongabay.co.id/2015/06/21/danauperta mbangan/
- http://www.mongabay.co.id/2015/06/30/hutanadatsubah-yang-menanti-sentuhannegara/
- http://pontianak.tribunnews.com/2015/05/31/darisektortambang-potensi-kehilanganuang-negara-bisaterjadi
- http://print.kompas.com/baca/2015/07/08/Hak-Warqayang-Terampas
- http://www.pontianakpost.co.id/url/mkuhengkanglingkungan-gersang
- http://www.mongabay.co.id/2015/04/28/pemetaan partisipatif-cara-efektif-wargasejotang-lindungihutanadat/
- http://print.kompas.com/baca/2015/07/08/Drone-%2cMurah%2c-Mudah%2c-dan-TidakBohong
- Nattpi://www.mongabay.co.id/2015/07/08/srikandipen gawal-danau-bekat-ini-keluhkanlimbah-tambang/

Spatial Transparency

Spatial Transparency in West Kalimantan. An open-access web-based GIS platform on promoting spatial transparency in land and forestry sector in West Kalimantan, Indonesia. http://editor.giscloud.com [eispatialtransparency]